"Iran is Israel's best friend,
’إيران هي الصديقة الحميمة لإسرائيل،
and we do not intend to change our position
و نحن نرغب في الحفاظ على تلك
in relation to Tehran."
العلاقة مع طهران."
Believe it or not, this is a quote
صدّقوا أو لا تصدّقوا، هذا اقتباس
from an Israeli prime minister,
عن رأيس الوزراء الإسرائيليّ،
but it's not Ben-Gurion or Golda Meir
لكن ليس بن غرويون أو غوالدا ماير
from the era of the Shah.
من حقبة الشاه.
It's actually from Yitzhak Rabin.
بل هو صادر من إسحاق رابين
The year is 1987.
بتاريخ 1987.
Ayatollah Khomeini is still alive,
كان آية الله الخميني لا يزال على قيد الحياة،
and much like Ahmadinejad today,
و كما يفعل أحمدي نجاد حاليّا،
he's using the worst rhetoric against Israel.
فهو كان يستعمل أسوأ خطابات ضدّ إسرائيل.
Yet, Rabin referred to Iran
لكن رابين تحدّث عن كون إيران
as a geostrategic friend.
بلدا صديقا استراتيجا.
Today, when we hear the threats of war
اليوم، عندما نسمع تهديدات الحرب
and the high rhetoric,
و الخطاب شديد اللهجة،
we're oftentimes led to believe
يجعلنا ذلك نفكر في العادة
that this is yet another one of those unsolvable
أنّ هذا هو صراع ثان غير قابل للحلّ
Middle Eastern conflicts
بمنطقة الشرق الأوسط
with roots as old as the region itself.
ذو اسباب قديمة بقدم المنطقة نفسها.
Nothing could be further from the truth,
ما من شيء كان أكثر مخالفة للحقيقة من هذا،
and I hope today to show you why that is.
و آمل أن أكشف لكم اليوم سبب ذلك.
The relations between the Iranian and the Jewish people
العلاقات بين الشعب الإيرانيّ و الشعب الإسرائيلي
throughout history has actually been quite positive,
كانت إيجابيّة جدّا خلال عصور من الزّمن،
starting in 539 B.C.,
منذ سنة 539 ق.م.
when King Cyrus the Great of Persia
عندما حرّر كورش الكبير، الملك الفارسيّ
liberated the Jewish people from their Babylonian captivity.
اليهود من استعباد البابليّين لهم.
A third of the Jewish population
ثلث المجتمع اليهوديّ
stayed in Babylonia.
بقي في بابل.
They're today's Iraqi Jews.
وهم يشكّلون يهود العراق حاليّا.
A third migrated to Persia.
ثلث آخر هاجر إلى بلاد الفرس.
They're today's Iranian Jews,
وهو اليوم يشكّلون يهود إيران،
still 25,000 of them living in Iran,
لايزال 25 ألفا منهم يعيش في إيران،
making them the largest Jewish community
ممّا يجعلهم أكبر مجتمع يهودي بالشرق
in the Middle East outside of Israel itself.
الأوسط دون احتساب يهود إسرائيل نفسها.
And a third returned to historic Palestine,
أمّا الثلث الآخر فقد عاد إلى فلسطين القديمة،
did the second rebuilding of the Temple in Jerusalem,
قاموا بإعادة بناء المعبد في القدس،
financed, incidentally, by Persian tax money.
و كانت عائدات ضرائب الفرس هي مموّلهم.
But even in modern times,
لكن حتّى في العصور الحديثة، فإنّ العلاقات
relations have been close at times.
بين البلدين كانت جيدة في بعض الأوقات.
Rabin's statement was a reflection
إفادة (رابين) تعكس
of decades of security and intelligence collaboration
عقودا من التّعاون الاستخباراتيّ و الأمنيّ
between the two, which in turn
بين البلدين، و الذي
was born out of perception of common threats.
نشأ من إدراك وحدة التهديدات.
Both states feared the Soviet Union
كلاهما كانتا تخافان الاتحاد السوفياتيّ
and strong Arab states such as Egypt and Iraq.
و البلدان العربية القوية كمصر و العراق.
And, in addition, the Israeli doctrine of the periphery,
فضلا عن العقيدة الإسرائيلية
the idea that Israel's security was best achieved
بأنّ أمنها سيتحقّق بصفة أفضل
by creating alliances with the non-Arab states
من خلال التّحالف مع الدول الغير عربية
in the periphery of the region
الموجودة بالمنطقة
in order to balance the Arab states in its vicinity.
لأجل تحقيق توازن في المنطقة مع البلدان العربية.
Now, from the Shah's perspective, though,
لكن من وجهة نظر الشاه،
he wanted to keep this as secret as possible,
فقد أراد أن يبقي الأمر سرّيا على قدر المستطاع،
so when Yitzhak Rabin, for instance,
لذلك و على سبيل المثال، عندما سافر
traveled to Iran in the '70s,
(إسحاق رابين) إلى إيران في السبعينات،
he usually wore a wig
كان يرتدي شعرا مستعارا
so that no one would recognize him.
حتّى لا يتعرّف عليه أحد.
The Iranians built a special tarmac
لقد بني الإيرانيون مدرّجا خاصا
at the airport in Tehran, far away from the central terminal,
في مطار طهران بعيدا عن مركز محطة الطيران،
so that no one would notice the large number
حتّى لا يلاحظ أحد الأعداد الكبيرة من
of Israeli planes shuttling between Tel Aviv and Tehran.
الطائرات الإسرائيلية المسافرة بين تل أبيب و طهران.
Now, did all of this end with the Islamic revolution
وهل انتهى كلّ هذا بحدوث الثورة الإسلامية
in 1979?
سنة 1979؟
In spite of the very clear anti-Israeli ideology
رغم الإيديولوجيا المعادية لإسرائيل
of the new regime, the geopolitical logic
لنظام الحكم الجديد إلاّ أنّ المنطق الجيوسياسي
for their collaboration lived on,
لتعاونهم قد استمرّ
because they still had common threats.
بسبب استمرار وجود تهديدات مشتركة.
And when Iraq invaded Iran in 1980,
و عند احتلال عراق لإيران عام 1980،
Israel feared an Iraqi victory
خشيت إسرائيل من نصر عراقيّ
and actively helped Iran by selling it arms
و ساعدت إيران عبر بيع أسلحتها
and providing it with spare parts
و توفير قطع الغيار
for Iran's American weaponry
للأسلحة الإيرانية الامريكية الصنع
at a moment when Iran was very vulnerable
في وقت كانت فيه إيران ضعيفة جدّا
because of an American arms embargo
بسبب حظر الأسلحة الأمريكية
that Israel was more than happy to violate.
و الذي كانت إسرائيل مستعدة لتجاهله.
In fact, back in the 1980s,
في الواقع، في الثمانينات،
it was Israel that lobbied Washington
كانت إسرائيل هي من ضغطت على واشنطن
to talk to Iran, to sell arms to Iran,
لتتحدّث مع إيران و تبيعها أسلحتها
and not pay attention to Iran's anti-Israeli ideology.
و بغضّ النّظر عن الإيديولوجيا المعادية لإسرائيل.
And this, of course, climaxed
و هذا بالطبع بلغ ذروته
in the Iran-Contra scandal of the 1980s.
في فضيحة إيران كونترا في الثمانينات.
But with the end of the Cold War
لكن مع نهاية الحرب الباردة،
came also the end of the Israeli-Iranian cold peace.
انتهى السلام البارد بين إيران و إسرائيل.
Suddenly, the two common threats
فجأة، كان التهديدان المشتركان
that had pushed them closer together throughout decades,
الذي دفعا البلدين للتمتين العلاقات معا طيلة عقود،
more or less evaporated.
قد تلاشى.
The Soviet Union collapsed,
انهار الاتحاد السوفياتي،
Iraq was defeated,
و انهزمت العراق
and a new environment was created in the region
و نشأت بيئة جديدة في المنطقة
in which both of them felt more secure,
أحسّ كلا البلدين فيها بالأمان،
but they were also now left unchecked.
لكن كان هناك خطر محدّق من جهة اليسار.
Without Iraq balancing Iran,
دون وجود العراق لتوازن إيران،
Iran could now become a threat,
من الممكن أن تصبح إيران الآن مصدر تهديد،
some in Israel argued.
كما فكّر بعض الإسرائيليين.
In fact, the current dynamic
في الواقع فإنّ التيار الديناميكيّ
that you see between Iran and Israel
الذي نراه بين إيران و إسرائيل
has its roots more so
ذو جذور تعود إلى
in the geopolitical reconfiguration of the region
أبعد في المجال الجيوسياسي بالمنطقة
after the Cold War
بعد الحرب الباردة
than in the events of 1979,
قبل أحداث سنة 1979،
because at this point, Iran and Israel
لأنّه و إلى ذلك الحين، كانت إيران و إسرائيل
emerge as two of the most powerful states in the region,
تبدوان كأكثر الدول قوة في المنطقة،
and rather than viewing each other
و عوض أن ترى بعضها البعض
as potential security partners,
كشركاء أمنيّين محتملين،
they increasingly came to view each other
أصبحا يران بعضهما البعض
as rivals and competitors.
كأعداء و متنافسين.
So Israel, who in the 1980s
إسرائيل التي سعت في الثمانينات
lobbied for and improved U.S.-Iran relations
لتحسين العلاقات بين إيران و الولايات المتحدة
now feared a U.S.-Iran rapprochement,
أصبحت الآن تخاف تقرّبا بين البلدين
thinking that it would come
ظنّا منها أنّ الأمر سيكون على حساب
at Israel's security interests' expense,
المصالح الأمنية الإسرائيلية،
and instead sought to put Iran
لذلك فقد أصبح تسعى لوضع إيران
in increased isolation.
في عزلة متنامية.
Ironically, this was happening at a time
المثير للسخرية هو كون هذا قد حدث
when Iran was more interested
في وقت كانت فيه إيران أكثر اهتماما
in peacemaking with Washington
بالتصالح السلمي مع واشنطن
than to see to Israel's destruction.
أكثر من اهتمامها بتدمير إسرائيل.
Iran had put itself in isolation
وضع تإيران نفسها في عزلة
because of its radicalism,
بسبب تطرّفها،
and after having helped the United States indirectly
و بعد مساعدة الولايات المتحدة بطريقة غير مباشرة،
in the war against Iraq in 1991,
في الحرب ضدّ العراق سنة 1991،
the Iranians were hoping
كان الإيرانيّون يأملون
that they would be rewarded by being included
في مكافأتهم من خلال ادراجهم ضمن
in the post-war security architecture of the region.
الهندسة الأمنية بالمنطقة بعد الحرب.
But Washington chose to ignore Iran's outreach,
لكن واشنطن اختارت تجاهل محاولات إيران التّواصل،
as it would a decade later in Afghanistan,
كما فعلت بعد عقد آخر مع أفغانستان،
and instead moved to intensify Iran's isolation,
و عملت على زيادة غزلة إيران،
and it is at this point, around 1993, '94,
و إلى تلك الفترة، بين 1993 و 1994،
that Iran begins to translate
بدأت إيران بتحويل
its anti-Israeli ideology
إيديولوجيتها المعادية لإسرائيل
into operational policy.
إلى سياسة عمليّة.
The Iranians believed that whatever they did,
كان الإيرانييون بعتقدون أنّ مهما فعلوا،
even if they moderated their policies,
حتّى لو أصبحت سياساتهم معتدلة،
the U.S. would continue to seek Iran's isolation,
فإنّ الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية ستواصل عزل البلاد
and the only way Iran could compel Washington
و الطريقة الوحيدة التي ستجبر بها واشنطن
to change its position was by imposing a cost
لتغيير رأيها هي من خلال فرض تكلفة
on the U.S. if it didn't.
على الولايات المتحدة لكنها لم تفعل.
The easiest target was the peace process,
أسهل طريقة كانت عملية السلام،
and now the Iranian ideological bark
و الآن أصبح نباح الإيديولوجيا الإيرانية
was to be accompanied by a nonconventional bite,
أصبح مصحوبا بطُعم غير تقليدي
and Iran began supporting extensively
و أصبحت إيران تساند المجموعات
Palestinian Islamist groups that it previously
الفلسطينية الإسلامية على نطاق واسع
had shunned.
التي كانت تتجنّبها سابقا.
In some ways, this sounds paradoxical,
قد يبدو هذا متناقضا،
but according to Martin Indyk
لكن حسب مارتن إينديك،
of the Clinton administration,
من إدارة حكومة كلينتون،
the Iranians had not gotten it entirely wrong,
فإنّ الإيرانيين لم يفهموا الأمر بطريقة خاطئة،
because the more peace there would be
لأنّ سلاما أكثر بين
between Israel and Palestine,
إسرائيل و فلسطين
the U.S. believed, the more Iran would get isolated.
يعني أنّ عزلة إيران سيزيد، حسب رأي الأمريكان.
The more Iran got isolated, the more peace there would be.
و كلّما ازدادت عزلة إيران، كلما كان هناك أكثر سلاما.
So according to Indyk, and these are his words,
إذن فحسب إيديك، وقد كانت تلك كلماته،
the Iranians had an interest to do us in
فإنّ من مصلحة إيران أن تمنع
on the peace process
عملية السّّلام
in order to defeat our policy of containment.
حتّى تتمكّن من هزم سياسة العزل الأمريكية.
To defeat our policy of containment,
لهزم سياسة العزل الأمريكية،
not about ideology.
لا يتعلّق الأمر بالإيديولوجية.
But throughout even the worst times of their entanglement,
لكن حتّى خلال أسوأ الأوقات من العزل،
all sides have reached out to each other.
كان هناك اتصال بين كل الأطراف.
Netanyahu, when he got elected in 1996,
عندما تمّ انتخاب ناتينياهو سنة 1996،
reached out to the Iranians to see
حاول الاتصال بالإيرانيين
if there were any ways that
للبحث عن أيّ طرق
the doctrine of the periphery could be resurrected.
يمكن بها استعادة عقيدة المحيط الجغرافيّ.
Tehran was not interested.
لم تكن طهران مهتمّة.
A few years later, the Iranians sent
بعد بعض سنوات، أرسل الإيرانيون
a comprehensive negotiation proposal to the Bush administration,
اقتراح تفاوض لإدارة الرّئيس بوش،
a proposal that revealed that there was some potential
اقتراح كان قد كشف أنّه لا يزال هناك امكانية
of getting Iran and Israel back on terms again.
إعادة العلاقات الإسرائيلية الإيرانية لسابق عهدها.
The Bush administration did not even respond.
إدارة بوش لم تجب أبدا.
All sides have never missed an opportunity
كلّ الأطراف لم يضيّعوا أيّ فرصة
to miss an opportunity.
تضييع فرصة.
But this is not an ancient conflict.
لكن هذا ليس بصراع قديم.
This is not even an ideological conflict.
و ليس حتّى صراعا إيديولوجيّا.
The ebbs and flows of hostility
لم تتغيّر التجاذبات العدائية
have not shifted with ideological zeal,
بسبب تعصّب الأيديولوجيات
but rather with changes in the geopolitical landscape.
لكن بسبب التغييرات في المشهد الجيوسياسي.
When Iran and Israel's security imperatives
عندما اقتضت الضرورة الأمنية التّعاون،
dictated collaboration, they did so
أصبحت إسرائيل و إيران حلفاء
in spite of lethal ideological opposition to each other.
رغم شدة التناقض المميت بين إيديولوجيّتي البلدين.
When Iran's ideological impulses collided
عندما تصادمت الدوافع الإيديولوجية مع
with its strategic interests,
المصالح الاستراتيجية،
the strategic interests always prevailed.
كانت الغلبة للمصالح الاستراتيجية.
This is good news, because it means
وهذا خبر سارّ لأنّه يعني
that neither war nor enmity
أنّ ما من عداوة أو صداقة
is a foregone conclusion.
ستكون دائما طبيعة العلاقة بينهما.
But some want war.
لكن البعض يسعى للحرب.
Some believe or say that it's 1938,
يعتقد البعض أنّها سنة 1938 حيث
Iran is Germany,
إيران هي ألمانيا
and Ahmadinejad is Hitler.
و أحمدي نجاد هو هتلر.
If we accept this to be true,
إن قمنا بتقبّل ذلك كحقيقة، كوننا
that indeed it is 1938, Iran is Germany,
نعيش واقعا مشابها لسنة 1938، إيران هي ألمانيا،
Ahmadinejad is Hitler,
و أحمدي نجاد هو هتلر،
then the question we have to ask ourself is,
إذن فيجب أن نطرح هذا السّؤال على أنفسنا،
who wishes to play the role of Neville Chamberlain?
من يرغب في لعب دور نيفيل شامبرلاين؟
Who will risk peace?
من سيخاطر بالسلام؟
This is an analogy that is deliberately aimed
إنّ تشبيه إيران بألمانيا يهدف
at eliminating diplomacy,
للقضاء على الديبلوماسية،
and when you eliminate diplomacy,
و عند القضاء على الديبلوماسية،
you make war inevitable.
تصبح الحرب أمرا حتميّا.
In an ideological conflict, there can be no truce,
في حرب إيديولوجية، لا مكان لهدنة،
no draw, no compromise,
استسلام أو تسوية،
only victory or defeat.
هناك أمّا النّصر أو الهزيمة.
But rather than making war inevitable
لكن عوض جعل الحرب حتميّة
by viewing this as ideological,
من خلال النظر على الأمر أنّ إيديولوجيّ،
we would be wise to seek ways
علينا أن نبحث عن طرق
to make peace possible.
لجعل السلام ممكنا.
Iran and Israel's conflict is a new phenomenon,
الصراع بين إيران و إسرائيل هو ظاهرة جديدة،
only a few decades old
تعود إلى بعض عقود في الماضي،
in a history of 2,500 years,
في تاريخ من 2500 سنة،
and precisely because its roots are geopolitical,
و بما أنّ أسبابه جيوسياسية بحتة،
it means that solutions can be found,
فهذا يعني أنّ الحلول ممكنة،
compromises can be struck,
و التسوية ممكنة،
however difficult it yet may be.
مهما تكن صعوبة الموقف.
After all, it was Yitzhak Rabin himself who said,
ففي النّهاية لقد كان إسحاق رابين هو القائل:
"You don't make peace with your friends.
"لا تصنع السلام مع أصدقائك،
You make it with your enemies."
بل مع أعدائك."
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)